Guide to the Anne T. Lawrence Mine Workers Oral History collection, 1972-1973 LAC0006
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Oral History Audio Cassettes, 1972 March 5-October 3; Series 1
  - Spencer Mullins and Laura Adkins Mullins Interview, 1972 September 27 (Box 2, Cassette 41)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 156 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Spencer and Laura Mullins lived in Verdunville, West Virginia. A lifelong miner around Omar, Mr. Mullins did not hear of union ideas until after returning from World War I. He states that the union sentiment really built up during the Depression. Mrs. Mullins discussed the life in the mining camps raising children.
  - Shirley Workman Interview, circa 1972 (Box 2, Cassette 59)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 158 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Shirley Workman lived in Mud Fork, West Virginia. Mrs. Workman's husband Issac worked over forty years for the Island Creek Coal Company. Mr. Workman joined the union prior to the Battle of Blair Mountain, but kept that information private for fear of persecution. Both Mr. Workman and two of his sons acquired black lung, and another was killed in a mine explosion at the #22 Holden mine. The Workman's see the coal companies as heartless bottom liners.
  - Albert Williamson Interview, 1972 September 27 (Box 2, Cassette 55)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 159 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Albert Williamson lived in Verdunville, West Virginia. Mr. Williamson worked in virtually all of the mines in Logan County until an accident forced early retirement in 1956. He discussed working conditions in non-union mines and how most miners could not wait for union organization that eventually came in 1933.
  - Nathan England Interview, 1972 September 28 (Box 1, Cassette 14)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 160 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Nathan England lived in Monaville, West Virginia. Mr. England discussed living and working conditions of the mines in Tennessee. Similar to other miners, he was afraid to discuss union sentiment for fear of being fired and blacklisted. He recalled stories of union organizing in Tennessee which were similar to the stories of union organizing in West Virginia. He moved to the county in the late 1930's and worked in the mines for over 30 years.
  - John Lee "Jack" Wilson Interview, circa 1972 (Box 2, Cassette 57, Cassette 58)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 166 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    John Lee "Jack" Wilson lived in Roda, Virginia. Mr. Wilson was an organizer for the Hazard County, Kentucky mines and was sent in by the U.M.W.A. into Harlan County, Kentucky. Mr. Wilson was faced with major violence upon arrival, and did not appreciate the union structure and their inactivity during that time. He was then blacklisted and moved to Roda, VA, where he worked under a different name.
  - William Glover Interview, 1972 August 6 (Box 1, Cassette 21)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 171 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    William Glover lived in St. Paul, Virginia. An unofficial organizer, Mr. Glover acted the part of contact from the unions to the working men in the mines in several areas of Virginia and Kentucky.
  - O. Litchfield Richardson Interview, circa 1972 (Box 2, Cassette 58)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 176 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    O. Litchfield Richardson lived in Norton, Virginia. Mr. Richardson was not interested in discussing his history, but he was involved with the first local union in Tom's Creek, VA in 1935.
  - Bill Gibson Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 20)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 178 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Bill Gibson lived in Norton, Virginia. He was a former president of the local union in Tom's Creek, VA. Mr. Gibson discussed the situation after the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933 and how the men organized.
  - Grant Howard Interview, 1972 July 19 (Box 1, Cassette 32)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 179 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground". This was a joint oral history with Grant Howard and Chester "Red" Poore.
    Grant Howard lived in Evarts, Kentucky. Both Grant Howard and Red Poore were veterans of the union movement in Harlan County, Kentucky and the Battle of Evarts. One of the skirmishes in 1931 resulted in two men killed, and Mr. Poore was sentenced to life imprisonment but only served a 10 year sentence. Mr. Poore discussed the lack of a union presence in 1972, even though men fought and died for the right to organize. Mr. Howard moved on from the coal mines to the steel mines, where he has a longer commute but a higher standard of living.
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Jackson_TRanscript
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Jackson_TRanscript
  - Chester "Red" Poore Interview, 1972 July 19 (Box 1, Cassette 32)
    Chester "Red" Poore lived in Evarts, Kentucky. Both Grant Howard and Red Poore were veterans of the union movement in Harlan County, Kentucky and the Battle of Evarts. One of the skirmishes in 1931 resulted in two men killed, and Mr. Poore was sentenced to life imprisonment but only served a 10 year sentence. Mr. Poore discussed the lack of a union presence in 1972, even though men fought and died for the right to organize. Mr. Howard moved on from the coal mines to the steel mines, where he has a longer commute but a higher standard of living.
  - Ben Foster Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 17, Cassette 16)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 185 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Ben Foster lived in Evarts, Kentucky. Mr. Foster discussed the efforts of organizing unions in Harlan County, Kentucky, as well as living and working conditions in the mines.
  - Bill Gibson Interview, 1972 July 20 (Box 1, Cassette 29)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 210 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Bill Gibson lived in Evarts, Kentucky. Mr. Gibson claims to be a union man and was present during the bad times of the early 1930s in Harlan County, Kentucky. He discussed living conditions in the towns and the mine conditions under operators that did not approve of union activity.
  - George W. Fritts Interview, 1972 July 20 (Box 1, Cassette 17, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 212 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    George Fritts lived in Evarts, Kentucky. Mr. Fritts was a taxi driver for both sides during the trial in Mt. Sterling as a result of the Battle of Evarts. He discussed the situations surrounding the trial and the treatment of both the miners and the coal operators.
  - John Bates Interview, 1972 June 17 (Box 1, Cassette 1)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 215 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    John Bates lived in Whitesburg, Kentucky. Mr. Bates worked as an organizer for Letcher County in 1933 and was a strong union supporter. He discussed living conditions during very violent times and outlined the measures took by union organizers.
  - Luther King Interview, 1972 June 18 (Box 2, Cassette 36)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 218 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Luther King lived in Whitesburg, Kentucky. As an organizer for the U.M.W.A. from 1931-33, Mr. King handled most of southeastern Kentucky. He discussed the difficulty in organizing and the operation of feeding striking miners and their families.
  - Dewey Brown Interview, 1972 June 17 (Box 1, Cassette 5)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 221 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Dewey Brown lived in Whitesburg, Kentucky. Mr. Brown worked as a volunteer organizer for the union in 1933 in Letcher County. He discussed the conditions of the mines prior to the union and the resulting conditions after the union was organized. He stated that only one union mine remained in 1972.
  - Joe Ramsay Interview, 1972 June 17 (Box 2, Cassette 47, Cassette 48)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 223 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Joe Ramsay lived in Monaville, West Virginia. He originally worked in the mines with his father in Letcher County, but moved Jenkins, Kentucky in 1933 where he was first exposed to the U.M.W.A. He eventually moved to Logan County, West Virginia, where he lived at the time of the interview.
  - WJ Martin Interview, 1972 June 12 (Box 2, Cassette 37, Cassette Side A)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and was not included in the report "On Dark and Bloody Ground."
  - Charles Hampton Interview, 1972 July 20 (Box 1, Cassette 29, Cassette Side B)
  - Charles & Mae Hampton Interview, 1972 July 20 (Box 1, Cassette 31)
  - Pat Fuller Interview, 1972 August 4 (Box 1, Cassette 18, Cassette Side A)
    Interview was conducted by an unidentified interviewer and was not included in the report "On Dark and Bloody Ground."
  - George Jackson Interview, 1972 August 16 (Box 1, Cassette 28, Cassette Side A)
  - Josephine Roche Interview, circa 1972 (Box 2, Cassette 49)
- Oral History Transcripts, circa 1972; Series 2
- NEH Report - "On Dark and Bloody Ground - An Oral History of the UMWA in Central Appalachia, 1920-1935", 1973 January; LAC0006 (Box Shared Box 32, Folder 2)